<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>dbt on Evgenii Karimov</title><link>https://www.karimov.berlin/tags/dbt/</link><description>Recent content in dbt on Evgenii Karimov</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>EN</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.karimov.berlin/tags/dbt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Combining dbt and SQLFluff</title><link>https://www.karimov.berlin/writing/2022-07-04-dbt-sqlfluff/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.karimov.berlin/writing/2022-07-04-dbt-sqlfluff/</guid><description>In this post I&amp;rsquo;d like to share how to adopt two very useful tools SQLFluff, a SQL linter, and dbt, a data modelling tool, into a powerful combination and make it work with pre-commit to ensure all your SQLs are properly formatted.
Why to combine them at all? There are a lot of ways to write SQL: leading/trailing commas, lower-upper case of keywords, aliasing table and column names, etc.
Since every data engineer and analyst spends a lot of time reading SQL code, having a standard style helps to improve this process and also makes writing less error-prone.</description></item><item><title>Implementing slim CI for dbt with GitHub Actions</title><link>https://www.karimov.berlin/writing/2022-04-06-dbt-slim-ci/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.karimov.berlin/writing/2022-04-06-dbt-slim-ci/</guid><description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve started working with dbt, and have to say it&amp;rsquo;s quite amazing. With this post I&amp;rsquo;d like to share the approach for deploying only newly created/modified models, known as slim CI.
Imagine we have an Airflow instance executing our dbt DAG daily.
In case we introduce structural changes in our models, or simply by creating a new model, we don&amp;rsquo;t want to wait till Airflow starts on schedule. Also, we don&amp;rsquo;t want to fire the whole pipeline execution, because it might be costly to run it multiple times per day.</description></item></channel></rss>